Guide to the Arthur H. and Mary Marden Dean Lafayette Collection, 1520-1973
Lafayette Collection (Arthur H. and Mary Marden Dean Lafayette Collection), 1520-1973
- Series IX. Commemorative Medals, Badges, Coins, and Plaques, Depicting Lafayette.
  - Lafayette (Circular medal, goldened bronze, 26 mm), 1834 or 1835; 82 (Box 187)
    O: Bust of Lafayette in redingote, with the legend: General Lafayette, 1757-1834. R: The Untiring defender of Constitutional Liberty. White
  - Lafayette (Circular medal, silvered bronze, 26 mm), 1834 or 1835; 83 (Box 187)
  - Lafayette (Circular medal, bronze, 26 mm), 1834 or 1835; 84 (Box 187)
  - Lafayette (Circular medal, bronze, 26 mm), 1834 or 1835; 85 (Box 187)
  - Lafayette (Circular medal, bronze, 26 mm), 1834 or 1835; 86 (Box 187)
  - Lafayette (Circular medal, goldened bronze, 28 mm), 1876; 87 (Box 187)
    O: Bust of Lafayette in redingote, with the legend: General Lafayette around the edge. R: "Defender of American and French Liberty. Born 1757, Died 1834. Statue in New York Unveiled Sept. 6, 1876". The statue of "Lafayette arriving in America" was executed in 1872 by Frédéric Auguste Bartholdi, and in 1876 was placed in Union square, New York. "Liberty enlightening the World," the colossal statue on Liberty Island, in New York Harbor, is also Bartholdi's work. White
  - Lafayette (Circular medal, silvered bronze, 28 mm), 1876; 88 (Box 187)
    O: Bust of Lafayette in redingote, with the legend: General Lafayette around the edge. R: "Defender of American and French Liberty. Born 1757, Died 1834. Statue in New York Unveiled Sept. 6, 1876". White
  - Lafayette (Circular medal, silvered bronze, 28 mm), 1876; 89 (Box 187)
    O: Bust of Lafayette in redingote, with the legend: General Lafayette around the edge.R: "Defender of American and French Liberty. Born 1757, Died 1834. Statue in New York Unveiled Sept. 6, 1876". White
  - Lafayette (Circular medal, bronze, 28 mm), 1876; 90 (Box 187)
  - Lafayette (Circular medal, bronze, 28 mm), 1876; 91 (Box 187)
    O: Bust of Lafayette in redingote, with the legend: General Lafayette around the edge. R: "Defender of American and French Liberty. Born 1757, Died 1834. Statue in New York Unveiled Sept. 6, 1876".White
  - Lafayette and Washington(Circular medal, bronze, 28 mm), 1876; 92 (Box 187)
    O: Bust of Lafayette in redingote, with the legend: General Lafayette around the edge. R: Bust of Washington. Variation in the same series, issued by the New York Medal Club.White
  - Lafayette and Washington(Circular medal, bronze, 28 mm), 1876; 93 (Box 187)
  - Lafayette (Circular medal, bronze, 21 mm), 94 (Box 187)
    O: Bust of Lafayette in redingote, facing right, with the legend: General Lafayette around the edge. R: the American seal (a bald eagle with its wings outstretched [or "displayed," in heraldic terms], holding a bundle of 13 arrows in its left talon referring to the 13 original states, and an olive branch, in its right talon, together symbolizing that the United States of America has "a strong desire for peace, but will always be ready for war.") Not listed by Olivier, date unknown. White
  - "Lafayette Dollar" (silver, 38 mm), 1900; 95 (Box 187)
    O: Busts of Lafayette and Washington. R: Equestrian statue of Lafayette, with the following legend: "Erected by the Youth of the United States in Honor of General Lafayette. Paris 1900". This refers to the history of the statue: funds were raised by the school children of America until $50,000 was accumulated--enough to create it and offer it to the Government of France for the 1900 "Exposition Universelle". Initialy installed on Place du Carrousel, adjacent to the Louvre, the monument was moved to make room for the I.M. Pei glass pyramid. Today it is located near on the right bank of the Seine between the Pont des Invalides and Pont Alexandre III. The first Lafayette dollar was offered to President Loubet of France. Today this coin is rather difficult to find. White
  - Lafayette and Washington (circular, bronze and silvered bronze, 28 mm), 1917; 96 (Box 187)
    O: Busts of Lafayette and Washington + mention of Gaston Lavrillier, Paris Art R: 4 Juillet 1776 / 14 Juillet 1789. Journée de Paris 1917.
  - Lafayette and Washington (uniface, goldened bronze, 72 mm), 1917?; 97 (Box 187)
    O: Lafayette and Washington standing and shaking hands in front of American and French flags. Not listed by Olivier. Provenance unknown.
  - Lafayette and the Transatlantic Liner Named after Him (circular, bronze, 68 mm), 1930; 98 (Box 187)
    O: Portrait of young Lafayette in uniform, facing left, signature :"Delannoy". R: a liner, with the legend "Compagnie Générale Transatlantique" above, and below: "M.S. Lafayette le plus Grand Paquebot Français à Moteur." The "Lafayette" was actually the largest ocean liner in the French Line. When it arrived in New York for the first time in May 1930, six hundred New York City school children gathered to greet it, and a "Revolutionary" masquerade party was organized on board with Marquis Jacques de Dampierre, a descendant of Lafayette, as the master of ceremonies. His name was inscribed on the sidewalk in Wall Street, where it is still visible today. The boat was destroyed by fire in 1938. Blancheteau.
  - Lafayette, Washington, and a Replica of Mt. Vernon Erected in Paris, 1931; 99 (Box 187)
    O: Superimposed busts of Lafayette and Washington, with their names and the signature "Delannoy". R: the recreation of Mont Vernon for the 1931 Exposition Coloniale Internationale in Paris. The United States was the only non-European country exhibiting as a colonial power in 1931. The American building at the exposition was a close replica of George Washington's house at Mount Vernon, complete with "the bedroom set aside for Lafayette." Blancheteau.
  - Lafayette and Washington (Circular, very thin, goldened bronze [?], 76 mm), [1934 ?]; 100 (Box 187)
    O: Lafayette and Washington shaking hands, with the legend around the edge: "To the Glory of American Liberty."Not listed in Olivier. date unknown. Blancheteau.
  - Lafayette, Washington, and the Mt. Vernon Replica in Paris, 1934; 101 (Box 187)
    O: Bust of Lafayette, with his dates and the signature "Gatteaux". R: "America et Gallia Memores MCMXXXIV." This medal was struck in limited number for the centennial of Lafayette's death. This exemplar was apparently given by the French Government to Cornell's president. Other peer institutions (such as U. Penn and Stanford) have the same medal coming from the President's Office. Blancheteau.
  - Enveloppes, n.d.; 1 (Box 188)
    These envelopes used to contain the medals. A.D. White's handwriting is on some of them.
  - Two Bronze Medallions Designed by Sculptor David d'Angers (1788-1856) Showing Lafayette Portrayed as Julius Caesar Dressed in Toga and Laurels, 1 (Box 189)
    17 x 17 cm
    [Designed in 1830. Likely made later]
- Series X. Media
  - America [D.W. Griffith], DVD-203 (Box 190)
  - The Black Book, DVD-204 (Box 190)
  - The Howards of Virginia, DVD-205 (Box 190)
  - Jefferson, DVD-206 (Box 190)
  - Marie Antoinette, DVD-207 (Box 190)
  - Lafayette [Video cassette], V-1447 (Box 190)
  - Reign of Terror [Video cassette], V-1448 (Box 190)
  - America [Video cassette], V-1449 (Box 190)